You know, culture was born of the imagination,
تعلمون، الثقافة تخلق من الخيال
and the imagination -- the imagination as we know it --
والخيال -- الخيال كما نعرفه..
came into being when our species descended
بدأ منذ بدء جنسنا
from our progenitor, Homo erectus,
وهو من مزايا أسلافنا
and, infused with consciousness, began a journey that would carry it
وباندماجه مع الوعي، بدأت رحلة
to every corner of the habitable world.
ووصلت إلى كافة الأصقاع المأهولة
For a time, we shared the stage with our distant cousins, Neanderthal,
لزمن ما لقد تشاركنا مرحلة من أبناء عمومتنا، الإنسان البدائي
who clearly had some spark of awareness,
الذي كان له بريق واضح من الوعي
but -- whether it was the increase in the size of the brain,
لكن سواء أكان عن طريق زيادة في حجم الدماغ
or the development of language,
أو تطور في اللغة
or some other evolutionary catalyst --
أو تطور مادة كيميائية أخرى محفزة
we quickly left Neanderthal gasping for survival.
فلقد تركنا البدائية تتوق للنجاة بسرعة
By the time the last Neanderthal disappeared in Europe,
في الوقت الذي انتهت آخر أشكال البدائية في أوروبا
27,000 years ago,
منذ 27000 سنة
our direct ancestors had already,
كان أسلافنا...
and for 5,000 years,
ولمدة 5000 سنة
been crawling into the belly of the earth,
يزحفون إلى رحم الأرض
where in the light of the flickers of tallow candles,
وعلى أضواء الشموع وشحومها
they had brought into being
استطاعو الوصول إلى
the great art of the Upper Paleolithic.
العصر الحجري العظيم
And I spent two months in the caves of southwest France
لقد أمضيت شهرين في كهوف جنوب غرب فرنسا
with the poet Clayton Eshleman, who wrote a beautiful book called "Juniper Fuse."
مع الشاعر "كلايتون إشلمان" الذي ألف كتاباً رائعاً اسمه "Juniper Fuse"
And you could look at this art and you could, of course,
يمكنك الإطلاع على هذا الفن ويمكنك بالتأكيد..
see the complex social organization
رؤية المنظومة الاجتماعية المعقدة
of the people who brought it into being.
التي أوجدته
But more importantly, it spoke of a deeper yearning,
لكن الأهم، أنه تكلم عن شوق أعمق
something far more sophisticated than hunting magic.
عن شيء أكثر تعقيداً من السحر
And the way Clayton put it was this way.
والطريقة التي قدم كلايتون بها كانت على النحو التالي:
He said, "You know, clearly at some point,
يقول، "تعلم، واضح أنه من ناحية ..
we were all of an animal nature, and at some point, we weren't."
جميعنا كنا من طبيعة حيوانية، ولم نكن كذلك من ناحية أخرى."
And he viewed proto-shamanism as a kind of original attempt,
وهو يعرض الشامانية (طقس روحي) كمحاولة
through ritual, to rekindle a connection
عبر هذا الطقس لأعادة إحياء اتصال
that had been irrevocably lost.
قد ضاع بطريقة لايمكن استرجاعه فيها
So, he saw this art not as
لذلك فهو رأى هذا الفن ليس
hunting magic, but as postcards of nostalgia.
كالسحر، وإنما كمشاعر حنين
And viewed in that light,
وأظهر -على ضوء ماسبق-
it takes on a whole other resonance.
أنها تأخذ صدى مختلف تماماً
And the most amazing thing about the Upper Paleolithic art
والشيء المذهل في فن العصر الحجري
is that as an aesthetic expression,
أن التعبير الجمالي
it lasted for almost 20,000 years.
قد دام لمدة 20000 سنة
If these were postcards of nostalgia,
لو أنها كانت مشاعر حنين
ours was a very long farewell indeed.
تعبيراتنا كانت في مرمى النسيان مقارنة بتلك التعبيرات
And it was also the beginning of our discontent,
ولقد كانت بداية لسخطنا
because if you wanted to distill all of our experience
لأننا إذا أردنا تصفية جميع خبراتنا
since the Paleolithic, it would come down to two words:
منذ العصر الحجري حتى الآن، لأمكننا اختصارها بكلمتين:
how and why.
كيف ولماذا.
And these are the slivers of insight upon which cultures have been forged.
وهاتين الكلمتين هما من تبعات رؤية الثقافات الماضية
Now, all people share the same
الآن، كل الناس لديهم نفس...
raw, adaptive imperatives.
الخامة، التي هي ضرورة التأقلم
We all have children.
كلنا لدينا أطفال
We all have to deal with the mystery of death,
كلنا لدينا مشكلة لغز الموت
the world that waits beyond death,
والعالم الذي ينتظرنا بعد الموت
the elders who fall away into their elderly years.
الشيخوخة وسنين الكهولة
All of this is part of our common experience,
كل هذه الأمور هي جزء من خبرة معروفة
and this shouldn't surprise us, because, after all,
وهذا يجب أن لا يشكل مفاجئة بالنسبة إلينا، لأنه وبعد كل شيء
biologists have finally proven it to be true,
علماء الأحياء أكدوا أنه حقيقة --
something that philosophers have always dreamt to be true.
الشيء الذي طالما حلم الفلاسفة بأن يكون حقيقة
And that is the fact that we are all brothers and sisters.
وهي حقيقة أننا جميعاً أخوة وأخوات
We are all cut from the same genetic cloth.
أننا جميعاً من فصيلة جينية واحدة
All of humanity, probably, is descended from a thousand people
وهي البشرية، ربما من آلاف الناس
who left Africa roughly 70,000 years ago.
الذين غادرو أفريقيا منذ 70000 سنة
But the corollary of that is that,
ولكن خلاصة الكلام
if we all are brothers and sisters
أنه إذا كنا كلنا أخوة وأخوات
and share the same genetic material,
ونملك نفس المواد الجينية
all human populations share the same raw human genius,
وكل التعدادات البشرية تملك نفس الخامة البشرية
the same intellectual acuity.
ونفس البراعة الفكرية
And so whether that genius is placed
وسواء أكانت هذه الطبيعة البشرية قد وضعت
into -- technological wizardry
عبر تكنولوجيا سحرية
has been the great achievement of the West --
هي أعظم إنجاز في الغرب --
or by contrast, into unraveling the complex threads
أو تغايرت إلى انهيار المواضيع المعقدة
of memory inherent in a myth,
عن الذاكرة الخرافية
is simply a matter of choice and cultural orientation.
فإن الموضوع ببساطة عبارة عن خيار أو توجيه ثقافي
There is no progression of affairs
لا يوجد تطور متتالي
in human experience.
في الخبرة البشرية
There is no trajectory of progress. There's no pyramid
لا يوجد مسار معين للتطور. لايوجد هرم للتطور
that conveniently places Victorian England at the apex
لأن هذا الأمر سيضع الملكة فكتوريا وسلالتها على رأس الهرم
and descends down the flanks
وينحدر إلى الأسفل عبر الأطراف
to the so-called primitives of the world.
إلى ما يدعى بدائيو العالم.
All peoples are simply cultural options,
كل الناس ببساطة هم خيارات ثقافية
different visions of life itself.
رؤيات مختلفة من الحياة نفسها
But what do I mean by different visions of life
ولكن ما أقصده بقولي :(رؤيات مختلفة للحياة )
making for completely different
صنع فرص متفاوتة تماماً
possibilities for existence?
للوجود.؟
Well, let's slip for a moment into the greatest culture sphere
حسناً، دعونا نلقي نظرة على أعظم ميدان ثقافي
ever brought into being by the imagination,
تم إيجاده بالخيال
that of Polynesia.
من قبل بولينيزيا
10,000 square kilometers,
10000 كيلومتر مربع
tens of thousands of islands flung like jewels upon the southern sea.
عشرات الآلاف من الجزر النائية تشبه المجوهرات في البحر الجنوبي
I recently sailed on the Hokulea,
لقد أبحرت مؤخراً في "هوكوليا"
named after the sacred star of Hawaii,
المسماة تيمناً بالنجم المقدس في هاواي
throughout the South Pacific to make a film
عبر جنوب المحيط الهادئ لتصوير فيلم
about the navigators.
عن البحارة.
These are men and women who, even today, can name
هؤلاء هم رجال ونساء يمكنم تسميتهم - حتى اليوم-
250 stars in the night sky.
250 نجمة في سماء الليل
These are men and women who can sense the presence of distant atolls
هؤلاء رجال ونساء يمكنهم الشعور بوجود جزر بعيدة
of islands beyond the visible horizon,
جزر مابعد أفق الرؤية
simply by watching the reverberation of waves
ببساطة عن طريق متابعة ارتدادات الأمواج
across the hull of their vessel, knowing full well
من هياكل سفنهم، ويعلمون بقوة
that every island group in the Pacific
أن كل مجموعة جزر في المحيط الهادئ
has its unique refractive pattern
لها نمط انعكاس متميز
that can be read with the same perspicacity
يمكن قرائته بنفس الوضوح
with which a forensic scientist would read a fingerprint.
الذي يقرأ به الطب الشرعي بصمة إصبع في يومنا هذا
These are sailors who in the darkness, in the hull of the vessel,
في الظلام هؤلاء البحارة، في هياكل سفنهم
can distinguish as many as 32 different sea swells
يمكنهم تمييز 32 طول موجة مختلفة من أمواج البحر
moving through the canoe at any one point in time,
يتنقلون عبر قارب في أي نقطة وفي الوقت المناسب
distinguishing local wave disturbances
يميزون أي اضطرابات موجية
from the great currents that pulsate across the ocean,
من التيارات العظيمة التي تتذبذب عبر المحيط
that can be followed with the same ease
والتي يمكن تتبعها بنفس السهولة
that a terrestrial explorer would follow a river to the sea.
التي يتتبع فيها مستكشف في البر مسار نهر إلى البحر
Indeed, if you took all of the genius
بالتأكيد ، إذا أخذنا كل العبقرية
that allowed us to put a man on the moon
التي أوصلتنا إلى القمر
and applied it to an understanding of the ocean,
وسخرناها لكي نفهم المحيط
what you would get is Polynesia.
فما سنحصل عليه هو بولينيزيا
And if we slip from the realm of the sea
وإذا انتقلنا من ممكلة البحر
into the realm of the spirit of the imagination,
إلى مملكة روح الخيال
you enter the realm of Tibetan Buddhism.
فإننا ندخل إلى المملكة البوذية التبتية
And I recently made a film called "The Buddhist Science of the Mind."
ولقد صنعت مؤخراً فيلماً يدعى: "علم العقل البوذي"
Why did we use that word, science?
لماذا استخدمنا هذه الكلمة، "علم".؟
What is science but the empirical pursuit of the truth?
أليس العلم محاولة الوصول إلى الحقيقة.؟
What is Buddhism but 2,500 years
أوليست البوذية عبارة عن 2500 سنة
of empirical observation
من الملاحظة التجريبية
as to the nature of mind?
كطبيعة العقل.؟
I travelled for a month in Nepal with our good friend, Matthieu Ricard,
لقد سافرت لمدة شهر إلى نيبال مع صديقنا الطيب "ماثيو ريكارد"
and you'll remember Matthieu famously said to all of us
وستتذكرون يوماً ما ماثيو يقول لنا جميعاً
here once at TED,
مرة ما هنا في "تيد"
"Western science is a major response to minor needs."
العلم الغربي هو استجابة رئيسية لحاجة ثانوية
We spend all of our lifetime trying to live to be 100
لقد قضينا كل حياتنا محاولين العيش مئة سنة
without losing our teeth.
دون أن نخسر أسناننا
The Buddhist spends all their lifetime trying to understand the nature of existence.
أما البوذيون فقد أمضو حياتهم يحاولون فهم الوجود
Our billboards celebrate naked children in underwear.
لوحاتنا تحتفل بأطفال عراة بألبستهم الداخلية
Their billboards are manuals,
ولوحاتهم كتيبات تحتوي على التفاسير
prayers to the well-being of all sentient creatures.
وصلوات لتكون مخلوقات واعية وفعالة
And with the blessing of Trulshik Rinpoche, we began a pilgrimage
وبتبريكات "Trulshik Rinpoche" بدأنا حـــجنا
to a curious destination,
لوجهة فضولية
accompanied by a great doctor.
بمرافقة دكتور عظيم
And the destination was a single room in a nunnery,
وهذه الوجهة كانت غرفة مفردة في دير للراهبات
where a woman had gone into lifelong retreat
حيث دخلت امرأة إلى معتزل لمدى الحياة
55 years before.
منذ 55 سنة
And en route, we took darshan from Rinpoche,
وفي الطريق أخذنا دروس من "Rinpoche"
and he sat with us and told us about the Four Noble Truths,
لقد جلس معنا وأخبرنا عن الحقائق الأربعة النبيلة
the essence of the Buddhist path.
جوهر الطريقة البوذية
All life is suffering. That doesn't mean all life is negative.
أنه كون الحياة كلها معاناة ، لايعني أن الحياة كلها سلبية
It means things happen.
هذا يعني أن أي شيء ممكن أن يحدث
The cause of suffering is ignorance.
وسبب المعاناة هو الجهل
By that, the Buddha did not mean stupidity;
وبهذا فإن بوذا لايعني بذلك الغباء
he meant clinging to the illusion
هو يعني التشبث بوهم
that life is static and predictable.
أن الحياة مستقرة ويمكن التنبؤ بها
The third noble truth said that ignorance can be overcome.
الحقيقة النبيلة الثالثة تنص على أنه يمكن التغلب على الجهل
And the fourth and most important, of course,
أما الحقيقة الرابعة والأكثر أهمية
was the delineation of a contemplative practice
هي التخطيط للأفعال التأملية
that not only had the possibility
والتي لم تكن لديها احتمال
of a transformation of the human heart,
تحويل القلوب البشرية وحسب
but had 2,500 years of empirical evidence
وإنما قدمت 2500 سنة من الدلائل التجريبية
that such a transformation was a certainty.
على أن تحول كهذا هو حتمي
And so, when this door opened onto the face of a woman
وعندما تم فتح هذا الباب في وجه إمرأة
who had not been out of that room in 55 years,
لم تخرج من تلك الغرفة منذ 55 سنة
you did not see a mad woman.
فإنك لم تشاهد إمرأة مجنونة
You saw a woman who was more clear
وإنما شاهدت إمرأة بصفاء
than a pool of water in a mountain stream.
أكثر من صفاء بحيرة جبلية
And of course, this is what the Tibetan monks told us.
وبالطبع، هذا ما أخبرنا به رهبان التبتية:
They said, at one point, you know, we don't really believe
يقولون من ناحية نحن لا نصدق
you went to the moon, but you did.
أننا وصلنا إلى القمر، لكننا فعلنا
You may not believe that we achieve enlightenment
قد لا تصدق أننا حققنا التنوير
in one lifetime, but we do.
في الحياة ، لكننا فعلنا
And if we move from the realm of the spirit
وإذا انتقلنا من المملكة الروحية
to the realm of the physical,
إلى المملكة الفيزيائية
to the sacred geography of Peru --
إلى المملكة المقدسة للجغرافيا في البيرو...
I've always been interested in the relationships of indigenous people
لطالما اهتممت بعلاقات سكان الأرض الأصليين
that literally believe that the Earth is alive,
الذين آمنو بحيوية الأرض
responsive to all of their aspirations,
بطريقة تستجيب لتطلعاتهم
all of their needs.
جميع احتياجاتهم
And, of course, the human population
وبالطبع فإن البشرية
has its own reciprocal obligations.
لديها التزاماتها المتبادلة
I spent 30 years living amongst
لثد أمضيت 30 سنة بين
the people of Chinchero
سكان "Chincherro"
and I always heard about an event that I always wanted to participate in.
وكنت دائماً أسمع عن حدث لطالما أردت المشاركة فيه
Once each year, the fastest young boy
مرة في كل سنة، الولد الأسرع
in each hamlet is given the honor of becoming a woman.
في كل قرية يمنح شرف تحوله إلى امرأة
And for one day, he wears the clothing of his sister
وليوم واحد يرتدي ملابس أخته
and he becomes a transvestite,
ويتحول إلى متخنث
a waylaka. And for that day,
أو ما يسمى بالـ:"Waylaka" وبنفس اليوم
he leads all able-bodied men on a run,
يقود مجموعة من الرجال المؤهلين بدنياً في سباق
but it's not your ordinary run.
لكنه ليس سباق اعتيادي
You start off at 11,500 feet.
فإنه يبدأ على ارتفاع 11500 قدم
You run down to the base of the sacred mountain, Antakillqa.
تركض إلى أسفل الجبل المقدس "Antkilka"
You run up to 15,000 feet,
صعوداً لعلو 15000 قدم
descend 3,000 feet.
ثم تنزل 3000 قدم
Climb again over the course of 24 hours.
ثم تعود لتصعد لما قد يستغرق 24 ساعة
And of course, the waylakama spin,
وبالطبع فإن الـ:"Waylakamaspin"
the trajectory of the route,
الاسم الذي يطلق على مسار الطريق
is marked by holy mounds of Earth,
يتم تحديده بأكوام مقدسة من التراب
where coke is given to the Earth, libations of alcohol to the wind,
حيث تعاد الكوكا الى الأرض وينثر الكحول مع الرياح
the vortex of the feminine is brought to the mountaintop.
يؤخذ الدرز النسوي الرقيق إلى قمة الجبل
And the metaphor is clear: you go into the mountain as an individual,
والمجاز هنا واضح: أنك تدخل إلى الجبل كفرد
but through exhaustion, through sacrifice,
ومن خلال التعب والتضحية
you emerge as a community that has once again
وتخرج كمجتمع جدد مرة أخرى
reaffirmed its sense of place in the planet.
مكانه في الكوكب
And at 48, I was the only outsider ever to go through this,
وفي عمر يناهز الـ:48 كنت الشخص الوحيد من خارج هذه البلد يشارك في الحدث
only one to finish it.
الشخص الوحيد الذي وصل إلى النهاية
I only managed to do it by chewing more coca leaves in one day
وذلك لأنني استطعت أن أمضغ نبات الكوكا ليوم واحد
than anyone in the 4,000-year history of the plant.
أكثر من أي شخص على مدار حياة النبتة منذ 4000 سنة
But these localized rituals become pan-Andean,
لكن هذه الطقوس التي تكتسب طابع المحلية أصبحت لعموم دول الأنديز
and these fantastic festivals,
وهذه المهرجانات المبهرة
like that of the Qoyllur Rit'i, which occurs
مثل ذلك الذي يدعى"Qoyllur Rit'i" والذي يحدث
when the Pleiades reappear in the winter sky.
عندما تظهر الثريا مرة أخرى في سماء الشتاء
It's kind of like an Andean Woodstock:
إنها أشبه بخاصية مميزة للأنديز
60,000 Indians on pilgrimage
60000 من الهنود ينزلون إلى الحج
to the end of a dirt road
على طريق من التراب
that leads to the sacred valley, called the Sinakara,
يقود إلى وادي مقدس يدعى "Sinakara"
which is dominated by three tongues
والذي تتشعب فيه الفروع الثلاثة
of the great glacier.
للنهر الجليدي العظيم
The metaphor is so clear. You bring the crosses from your community,
المجاز واضح جداً. تأتي بالصلبان من مجتمعك
in this wonderful fusion of Christian
في هذا المزيج الرائع من المسيحية
and pre-Columbian ideas.
وأفكار ما قبل كولومبوس
You place the cross into the ice,
وتضع الصليب في الجليد
in the shadow of Ausangate, the most sacred of all Apus,
في ظلال جبل الـ:"Ausangate" الجبل الأكثر قدسية
or sacred mountains of the Inca.
في جبال الأنكا المقدسة
And then you do the ritual dances that empower the crosses.
ومن ثم تقوم بالرقصات الطقوسية التي تزيد قوة الصلبان
Now, these ideas and these events
هذه الأفكار وهذاه الأحداث
allow us even to deconstruct iconic places
تمكننا من التعمق في أماكن إبداعية
that many of you have been to, like Machu Picchu.
كثيراً منكم قد زارها من قبل مثل "Machu Picchu"
Machu Picchu was never a lost city.
هذه المدينة لم تكن مدينة مجهولة نهائياً
On the contrary, it was completely linked in
على العكس، كانت متناسقة تماماً
to the 14,000 kilometers of royal roads
على طول 14000 كم من الطرق الملكية
the Inca made in less than a century.
صنعها الإنكيين على مدار أقل من قرن
But more importantly, it was linked in
ولكن الأهم من ذلك أنها كانت موصولة
to the Andean notions of sacred geography.
مع التضاريس المقدسة لأمم الأنديز
The intiwatana, the hitching post to the sun,
الـ:"Intiwatana" , مايبهر في الأمر
is actually an obelisk that constantly reflects the light
هو في الحقيقة النصب العامودي الذي يعكس الضوء باستمرار
that falls on the sacred Apu of Machu Picchu,
ويسقطه على الجبل المقدس لـ:"Machu Picchu"
which is Sugarloaf Mountain, called Huayna Picchu.
وهو جبل يدعى "Huauna Picchu"
If you come to the south of the intiwatana, you find an altar.
إذا أتينا إلى جنوب الـ:Intiwatana سوف ترى معبداً
Climb Huayna Picchu, find another altar.
وإذا صعدنا إلى قمة جبل الـ:Huayna Picchu سوف ترى معبداً آخر
Take a direct north-south bearing,
وإذا أخذنا اتجاهاً شمالياً جنوبياً مباشراً
you find to your astonishment
سوف تصاب بالدهشة
that it bisects the intiwatana stone,
ستلاحظ أنه يشطر صخرة الـ:Intiwatana
goes to the skyline,
يذهب في الأفق
hits the heart of Salcantay, the second of the most important mountains
ويصيب قلب جبل الـ"Salcantay" الجبل الثاني من حيث الأهمية
of the Incan empire.
في إمبراطورية الإنكا
And then beyond Salcantay, of course,
ومن ثم من بعد Salcantay بالطبع
when the southern cross reaches the southernmost point in the sky,
عندما يصل التقاطع الجنوبي إلى أعلى نقطة في الشمال في السماء
directly in that same alignment, the Milky Way overhead.
مباشرة في نفس المحاذاة، درب التبانة من فوق
But what is enveloping Machu Picchu from below?
لكن مايغلف Machu Picchu من الأسفل
The sacred river, the Urubamba, or the Vilcanota,
النهر المقدس، الـ:Urubamba للـ:Vilcanota
which is itself the Earthly equivalent of the Milky Way,
والذي يكون نظير درب التبانة على الأرض
but it's also the trajectory that Viracocha walked
لكنه أيضاً مسار اتبعه Viracocha
at the dawn of time when he brought the universe into being.
في فجر التاريخ عندما أوجد الكون
And where does the river rise?
واحزرو من أين ينبع النهر.؟
Right on the slopes of the Koariti.
تماماً في منحدرات الـ:"Koiariti"
So, 500 years after Columbus,
لذلك فإنه منذ 500 سنة قبل كولومبوس
these ancient rhythms of landscape
هذه التوازنات القديمة من الطبيعة
are played out in ritual.
تمت صياغتها بطقوس روحية
Now, when I was here at the first TED,
عندما كنت هنا أول مرة في TED
I showed this photograph: two men of the Elder Brothers,
لقد عرضت هذه الصورة -- رجلين من الأخوة المسنين
the descendants, survivors of El Dorado.
هم أحفاد الناجين من الـ:Eldorado
These, of course, are the descendants
هؤلاء، بالطبع، هم أحفاد
of the ancient Tairona civilization.
خضارة الـ:Tairona القديمة
If those of you who are here remember that I mentioned
إذا كنتم ممن كانو معنا ذاك الوقت يذكرون أنني ذكرت
that they remain ruled by a ritual priesthood,
أنهم بقوا محكومون من قبل كهنة روحيين
but the training for the priesthood is extraordinary.
لكن التدريب لكي تكون كاهن هو أمر فوق الطبيعي
Taken from their families, sequestered in a shadowy world of darkness
حيث يؤخذون من عائلاتهم، ويعزلون في مكان غامض مظلم
for 18 years -- two nine-year periods deliberately chosen
لمدة 18 سنة -- فترتين مؤلفتين من تسعة سنين يتم اختيارهم بعناية فائقة
to evoke the nine months they spend in the natural mother's womb.
لاستحضار الشهور التسعة التي أمضوها في بطون أمهاتهم
All that time, the world only exists as an abstraction,
كل هذا الوقت العالم يبدو كأنه لوحة تجريدية
as they are taught the values of their society.
لأنهم تعلموا قيم مجتمعهم
Values that maintain the proposition that their prayers,
القيم التي ترسخ افتراض أن صلواتهم
and their prayers alone, maintain the cosmic balance.
ووحدها صلواتهم تبقي على التوازن الكوني
Now, the measure of a society is not only what it does,
إن مقياس مجتمع ما ليس فقط ما يقوم به هذا المجتمع
but the quality of its aspirations.
بل إلى مستوى تطلعاته
And I always wanted to go back into these mountains,
ولطالما أردت العودة إلى هذه الجبال
to see if this could possibly be true,
لأرى إن كان هذا معقولاً
as indeed had been reported by the great anthropologist,
على اعتبار أنه تم تقرير ذلك من مختص عظيم في علوم الإنسان
Reichel-Dolmatoff.
وهو: Reichel-Dolmatoff
So, literally two weeks ago,
منذ حوالي أسبوعين
I returned from having spent six weeks with the Elder Brothers
عدت بعد قضاء ستة أسابيع مع الأخوان المسنين
on what was clearly the most
الأمر الذي كان بشكل واضح
extraordinary trip of my life.
الرحلة الأكثر إثارة في حياتي
These really are a people who live and breathe
هؤلاء فعلاً هم الناس الذين يعيشون ويتنفسون
the realm of the sacred,
مملكة القدسية
a baroque religiosity that is simply awesome.
ذات تعابير تقوى هي ببساطة مدهشة
They consume more coca leaves than any human population,
إنهم يستهلكون أوراق الكوكا أكثر من أي حضارة بشرية
half a pound per man, per day.
نصف باوند للشخص يومياً
The gourd you see here is --
قرع النبات الذين ترونه هنا --
everything in their lives is symbolic.
كل شيئ في حياتهم رمزي
Their central metaphor is a loom.
المجاز المركزي عندهم هو عبارة عن نول نسيج
They say, "Upon this loom, I weave my life."
يقولون، على هذا المنسج أقوم بحبك حياتي
They refer to the movements as they exploit the ecological niches of the gradient
يعبرون عن التحركات بأنها استغلال بيئات إيكولوجية للمنحدر
as "threads."
كمواضيع
When they pray for the dead, they make these gestures with their hands,
عندما يصلون للأموات يقومون بهذه الحركات بأيديهم
spinning their thoughts into the heavens.
يغزلون أفكارهم إلى الجنان
You can see the calcium buildup on the head of the poporo gourd.
يمكنك مشاهدة البنية الكلسية لرأس نبات الـ:Poporo
The gourd is a feminine aspect; the stick is a male.
النبات هو المظهر الأنثوي والنتوء هو الذكر
You put the stick in the powder
تضع النتوء في البودرة
to take the sacred ashes -- well, they're not ashes,
لتأخذ الرماد المقدس -- حسناً إنه ليس رماد
they're burnt limestone --
إنها كلسيات محروقة --
to empower the coca leaf, to change
لتزيد من قوة ورقة الكوكا لتغير
the pH of the mouth to facilitate the absorption
حموضة الفم لتسهيل امتصاص
of cocaine hydrochloride.
هيدروكلوريد الكوكائين
But if you break a gourd, you cannot simply throw it away,
لكنك إذا كسرت قرعة نبات ، لايمكنك رميها
because every stroke of that stick
لأن كل قطعة من ذاك النتوء
that has built up that calcium,
الذي شكل الكلس فيه
the measure of a man's life,
مقياس حياة رجل ما
has a thought behind it.
توجد خلفه فكرة ما
Fields are planted in such an extraordinary way,
حقول تتم زراعتها بطريقة مبهرة
that the one side of the field
لدرجة أن أحد أطراف الحقل
is planted like that by the women.
تتم زراعته بهذه الطريقة من قبل النساء
The other side is planted like that by the men. Metaphorically,
والطرف الآخر تتم زراعته بهذه الطريقة من قبل الرجال، بشكل مجازي
you turn it on the side, and you have a piece of cloth.
وعندما تديره من طرف إلى آخر تحصل على مايشبه قطعة قماش
And they are the descendants of the ancient Tairona civilization,
وهؤلاء هم أحفاد حضارة الـ:Tairona القديمة
the greatest goldsmiths of South America,
عظماء جنوب أفريقيا من الصاغة
who in the wake of the conquest,
والذين في أعقاب الغزو
retreated into this isolated volcanic massif
انهزموا إلى الكتلة الصخرية البركانية المعزولة
that soars to 20,000 feet
التي ترتفع 20000 قدم
above the Caribbean coastal plain.
عن سطح ساحل الكاريبي
There are four societies:
هناك أربعة مجتمعات
the Kogi, the Wiwa, the Kankwano and the Arhuacos.
الـ:Kogi , Wiwa , Kankuamo , Arhuacos
I traveled with the Arhuacos,
لقد تجولت مع الـ:Arhuacos
and the wonderful thing about this story
والشيء الجميل في القصة
was that this man, Danilo Villafane --
أن هذا الرجل Danilo Viathanya
if we just jump back here for a second.
إذا عدنا للحظة هنا
When I first met Danilo, in the Colombian embassy in Washington,
في أول مرة قابلت فيها Danilo في السفارة الكولومبية في واشنطن
I couldn't help but say, "You know,
لم أستطع منع نفسي من القول له : ...
you look a lot like an old friend of mine."
أنت تشبه أحد أصدقائي القدامى
Well, it turns out he was the son of my friend, Adalberto,
في الواقع لقد كان ابن صديقي، Aroberto
from 1974, who had been killed by the FARC.
منذ 1974 والذي كان قد قتل من قبل القوات المسلحة الثورية الكولومبية
And I said, "Danilo, you won't remember this,
قلت له، ألا تذكر ذلك.؟
but when you were an infant, I carried you on my back,
لكنك عندما كنت رضيعاً حملتك على ظهري
up and down the mountains."
صعوداً ونزولاً على الجبال
And because of that, Danilo invited us
وعلى أثر ذلك دعانا Danilo
to go to the very heart of the world,
إلى قلب العالم
a place where no journalist had ever been permitted.
مكان لم يسمح للصحفيين زيارته من قبل
Not simply to the flanks of the mountains,
ليس ببساطة إلى حواف الجبال
but to the very iced peaks which are the destiny of the pilgrims.
بل إلى القمم المتجمدة التي تمثل وجهة الحجاج
And this man sitting cross-legged
وهذا الرجل الذي يجلس القرفصاء
is now a grown-up Eugenio,
هو عضو Yuhenio ناضج الآن
a man who I've known since 1974.
رجل عرفته منذ 1974
And this is one of those initiates.
وهذه إحدى المبادرات
No, it's not true that they're kept in the darkness for 18 years,
لا، ليس صحيحاً أنهم بقو في الظلام لمدة 18 سنة
but they are kept within the confines
لكنهم بقوا في حدود
of the ceremonial men's circle
في دائرة الرجال الشعائرية
for 18 years.
لمدة 18 سنة
This little boy will never step outside
هذا الصبي لن يغادر أبداً
of the sacred fields
الحقول المقدسة
that surround the men's hut for all that time,
التي تحيط بسكن الرجال دائماً
until he begins his journey of initiation.
حتى يبدأ رحلة مبادرته
For that entire time, the world only exists as an abstraction,
وخلال كل هذه المدة، العالم بالنسبة له هو عبارة عن تعبير تجريدي
as he is taught the values of society,
من خلال تعلمه قيم المجتمع
including this notion that their prayers alone
متضمنة نظرية أن صلواتهم لوحدها
maintain the cosmic balance.
تبقي على توازن الكون
Before we could begin our journey,
قبل أن نتمكن من بدء رحلتنا
we had to be cleansed at the portal of the Earth.
كان من المفترض تطهيرنا على بوابة الأرض
And it was extraordinary to be taken by a priest.
وتم ذلك من قبل الكاهن
And you see that the priest never wears shoes because holy feet --
ويمكنك ملاحظة أن الكاهن لا يرتدي أية حذاء بسبب قدسية أقدامه
there must be nothing between the feet
حيث من غير الممكن أن يفصل القدمان أي شيء
and the Earth for a mamo.
عن الأرض من أجل الـ:Mamo
And this is actually the place where the Great Mother
وهو بالحقيقة المكان الذي وضعت فيه الأم
sent the spindle into the world
المحور للعالم
that elevated the mountains and created the homeland
المحور الذي شيد الجبال وشكل الوطن...
that they call the heart of the world.
الذي يطلقون عليه "قلب العالم "
We traveled high into the paramo,
لقد تسلقنا عالياً في جبل الـ:Potomo
and as we crested the hills,
وبعد أن جبنا التلال
we realized that the men were interpreting
أدركنا أن الرجال كانو يفسرون
every single bump on the landscape
كل نتوء في المنظر الطبيعي
in terms of their own intense religiosity.
في ضوء تقواهم الشديدة
And then of course, as we reached our final destination,
وبعدها بالطبع، عندما وصلنا إلى وجهتنا النهائية
a place called Mamancana,
المكان الذي يدعى Mananakana
we were in for a surprise,
أصبنا بالدهشة
because the FARC were waiting to kidnap us.
لأن القوات المسلحة الثورية الكولمبية كانت تنتظرنا لتخطفنا
And so we ended up being taken aside into these huts,
وانتهى بنا الأمر إلى هذه الأكواخ
hidden away until the darkness.
مخبئين حتى حلول الظلام
And then, abandoning all our gear,
ومن ثم تخلينا عن كافة أمتعتنا
we were forced to ride out in the middle of the night,
لقد أُجبرنا على المضي في منتصف الليل
in a quite dramatic scene.
في مشهد صامت دراماتيكي
It's going to look like a John Ford Western.
كان أشبه بفيلم غربي لـ:John Ford
And we ran into a FARC patrol at dawn, so it was quite harrowing.
ثم تصادمنا مع دورية من القوات المسلحة الثورية الكولمبية عند بزوغ الفجر، كان شيئ مروع
It will be a very interesting film. But what was fascinating
سيكون ذلك فيلماً مثيراً. لكن ما كان مدهشاً
is that the minute there was a sense of dangers,
أنه في لحظة وجود إحساس بالخطر
the mamos went into a circle of divination.
الـ:Mamos أخذو يبدأون بالتبصير
And of course, this is a photograph
وبالطبع هذه الصورة
literally taken the night we were in hiding,
مأخوذة حرفياً في ليلة الاختباء
as they divine their route
عندما كانو يتكهنوا الطريق
to take us out of the mountains.
لإخراجنا من الجبال
We were able to, because we had trained
وكنا قادرين، بسبب تدريبنا
people in filmmaking,
للناس على صناعة الأفلام
continue with our work,
كنا قادرين على متابعة عملنا
and send our Wiwa and Arhuaco filmmakers
وأرسلنا الـ:Wiwa والـ:Arhuaco المختصين بصناعة الأفلام
to the final sacred lakes
إلى آخر البحيرات المقدسة
to get the last shots for the film,
لتصوير آخر مقاطع الفيلم
and we followed the rest of the Arhuaco back to the sea,
وعدنا مع من تبقى من الـ:Arhuaco إلى البحر
taking the elements from the highlands to the sea.
آخذين العناصر من أعلى الجبال إلى البحر
And here you see how their sacred landscape
وهنا ترى كيف أن المشهد المقدس
has been covered by brothels and hotels and casinos,
قد تم تغطيته ببيوت الدعارة والفنادق والكازينوهات
and yet, still they pray.
ومع ذلك، فإنهم مازالوا يصلون
And it's an amazing thing to think
ومن المدهش أن تفكر
that this close to Miami,
أنه وبهذا القرب من Miami
two hours from Miami, there is an entire civilization of people
ساعتان فقط ، يوجد حضارة كاملة من الناس
praying every day for your well-being.
تصلي كل يوم من أجل وجودك
They call themselves the Elder Brothers.
يدعون أنفسهم الأخوة الأكبر
They dismiss the rest of us who have ruined the world
ويطردون ما تبقى منا لأننا دمرنا العالم
as the Younger Brothers. They cannot understand
كأخوة أصغر سناً. لايمكنهم فهم
why it is that we do what we do to the Earth.
لماذا نفعل ما نفعله بالأرض
Now, if we slip to another end of the world,
إذا انتقلنا إلى نهاية أخرى للعالم
I was up in the high Arctic
فلقد ذهبت إلى أعلى القطب الشمالي
to tell a story about global warming,
لألقي قصة عن ارتفاع درجة حرارة الكرة الأرضية
inspired in part by
ملهماً من قبل
the former Vice President's wonderful book.
كتاب نائب الرئيس السابق
And what struck me so extraordinary
وما دفعني بقوة
was to be again with the Inuit --
أن أكون مرة أخرى مع شعب الإسكمو
a people who don't fear the cold, but take advantage of it.
والذين هم شعب لا يخافون البرد وإنما يستغلونه
A people who
هم شعب...
find a way, with their imagination,
أوجدوا طريقة من خلال مخيلتهم
to carve life out of that very frozen.
لنحت الحياة من هذه القطعة الجليدية
A people for whom blood on ice
الشعب الذي عندما يرون دماً على الجليد
is not a sign of death, but an affirmation of life.
ليس إشارة للموت وإنما تأكيداً على وجود الحياة
And yet tragically, when you now go to those northern communities,
ومع ذلك للأسف، عندما تذهب الآن إلى هذه المجتمعات الشمالية
you find to your astonishment
فإنك تصاب بالدهشة
that whereas the sea ice used to come in in September
لأنه في حين أن البحر الجليدي يستخدم للعبور في إيلول
and stay till July,
ويبقى كذلك حتى حزيران
in a place like Kanak in northern Greenland,
في مكان مثل Kanak في شمال Greenland
it literally comes in now in November
فإنه يعبر حرفياً في كانون الثاني
and stays until March.
ويبقى حتى آذار
So, their entire year has been cut in half.
بحيث أن سنتهم تكون على نصفين
Now, I want to stress that none of these peoples
أريد أن ألفت انتباهكم إلى أنه لا أحد من هؤلاء الناس
that I've been quickly talking about here
الذين كنت أتحدث عنهم هنا
are disappearing worlds.
هم عوالم قيد الانقراض
These are not dying peoples.
إنهم ليسو أناس يموتون
On the contrary, you know,
على العكس، تعلمون،...
if you have the heart to feel and the eyes to see,
إذا كنتم تملكون القلوب لتشعروا والعيون لتروا
you discover that the world is not flat.
تكتشفون أن العالم ليس مسطحاً
The world remains a rich tapestry.
العالم يبقى نسيجاً غنياً
It remains a rich topography of the spirit.
إنه يبقى طوبوغرافية غنية من الروحانية
These myriad voices of humanity
هذه الأصوات البشرية التي لا تعد ولا تحصى
are not failed attempts at being new,
ليست محاولات فاشلة للتجديد
failed attempts at being modern.
أو فاشلة للمعاصرة
They're unique facets of the human imagination.
إنها حقائق متميزة من مخيلة البشر
They're unique answers to a fundamental question:
إنها إجابات متميزة على التساؤلات الأساسية
what does it mean to be human and alive?
ماذا يعني كوننا بشر على قيد الحياة.؟
And when asked that question, they respond
وعندما يُسألون هذا السؤال، فإنهم يجيبون
with 6,000 different voices.
بـ:6000 أصوات مختلفة
And collectively, those voices become our human repertoire
وبشكل جماعي، هذه الأصوات تصبح مرجعاً لبشريتنا
for dealing with the challenges that will confront us
للتعامل مع التحديات التي سوف تواجهنا
in the ensuing millennia.
عبر آلاف السنين
Our industrial society is scarcely
إن مجتمعنا الصناعي بالكاد..
300 years old.
بلغ عمر الـ: 300 سنة
That shallow history shouldn't suggest to anyone
هذا التاريخ الضحل لا يجب أن يوحي لأي شخص
that we have all of the answers
أننا نملك كافة الإجابات
for all of the questions that will confront us
على كافة التساؤلات التي تواجهنا
in the ensuing millennia.
عبر آلاف السنين
The myriad voices of humanity are not failed attempts at being us.
الأصوات البشرية التي لا تعد ولا تحصى ليست محاولات فاشلة لكونها نحن
They are unique answers to that fundamental question:
إنها إجابات متميزة عن تساؤلات أساسية:
what does it mean to be human and alive?
ماذا يعني أن نكون بشراً وعلى قيد الحياة
And there is indeed a fire burning over the Earth,
وبالتأكيد هناك حرارة تحرق الأرض
taking with it not only plants and animals,
ليس فقط النباتات والحيوانات
but the legacy of humanity's brilliance.
وإنما أسطورة العبقرية البشرية أيضاً
Right now, as we sit here in this room,
في الوقت الحالي وبينما نجلس في هذه الغرفة
of those 6,000 languages spoken the day that you were born,
من بين الـ:6000 لغة المحكية منذ ولادتنا
fully half aren't being taught to children.
نصفها بالتحديد لايتم تعليمها للأطفال
So, you're living through a time
لذلك فإننا نعيش في زمن
when virtually half of humanity's intellectual,
تكون فيه نصف الإرث الفكري البشري
social and spiritual legacy
الاجتماعي والروحي
is being allowed to slip away.
يتم التخلي عنه
This does not have to happen.
وهذا يجب أن لايحدث
These peoples are not failed attempts at being modern --
هؤلاء الناس هم ليسو محاولات فاشلة للتجديد
quaint and colorful and destined to fade away
طريفة وملونة ومعدّة لتختفي بعيداً
as if by natural law.
وكأنها من قانون الطبيعة
In every case, these are dynamic, living peoples
في كل حالة، هناك أناس يعيشون بديناميكية
being driven out of existence by identifiable forces.
خلال رحلة الوجود عن طريق قوى تعريفية
That's actually an optimistic observation,
هذه في الحقيقة ملاحظة تفاؤلية
because it suggests that if human beings
لأنها تقترح أنه إذا كان البشر
are the agents of cultural destruction,
هم عملاء الخراب الثقافي
we can also be, and must be,
فمن ثم يمكننا أن نكون ، ويجب أن نكون
the facilitators of cultural survival.
المساهمين في نجاة الثقافة
Thank you very much.
شكراً جزيلاً لكم